打杂的奴隶不可能成为角斗士
House slaves will never be gladiators.
而我们缺的正是能打仗的人
A thing we are in short supply of.
钥匙拿来 快点
Keys, quickly!
放他们出来
Release them!
队伍扩大了
Our ranks swell.
我们需要更多武器
We will need more weapons.
感谢你的一片心意
Gratitude for your kindness,
我可是特别珍惜呢
Know that I have treasured it.
谣言是真的吗
Is it true?
你跟她上床了
Did you lay with her?
奥诺玛默斯
Oenomaus.
我要你干掉盖尤斯•克罗迪斯•葛雷博
I would have you end the life of Gaius Claudius Glaber.
葛雷博的妻子
Glaber's own wife,
今晚就要前往罗马
this very night leaves for Rome.
你的军队归我了
Your men are now mine.
《斯巴达克斯：复仇》
《对等》
你要把我带到哪里去
Where do you take me?
求求你 我怀有身孕
Please, I am with child
有人来了
Someone approaches.
老老实实跟我走
Follow fucking lead.
别耍心眼
And do not stray from it.
走吧
Come.
兄弟 你怎么走到这荒郊野地里来了
What brings you so far from road, brother?
还带着个孕妇
With one so ripe?
骑的老马一命呜呼了
An ancient horse, gone to grass.
这条路去庞贝比较近 省得我妻子劳累
The woods offer shorter distance for my wife to Pompeii.
要是不加小心 送命也快
Shorter by a lifetime, if tread absent caution.
斯巴达克斯和他手下那帮畜生
Spartacus and his fucks set upon a wagon
前几天在附近劫了辆马车
not far from here recently.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus?
亲爱的 我们应该赶紧上路了
Perhaps, we should be on our way, my love.
不然噩运也会降临到我们头上
Unless similar misfortune fall upon us.
看起来你们已经很倒霉了
Ah, it appears it already has.
你怎么这副模样
How did you come by that?
从马上摔下来时受的伤
Our horse, when it fell.
在去庞贝的路上 明白了
On the road to Pompeii, yes.
你在庞贝有生计
You have business there?
杀猪宰羊换几个钱
Meat and bone, carved for coin.
你是屠夫
A butcher?
屠夫的老婆穿这么好的衣服
Fine dress, for wife of such.
他是个角斗士
He's a gladiator!
我是民政官的…
I am the Praetor's
对不起了
Apologies.
救命啊
Help me!
谁来救救我
Somebody, help me!
救命
Help me!
你再出一声
Raise voice again,
我就把你的舌头割下来
and I will hack tongue from fucking mouth.
你出个价钱
Ask any price.
我丈夫肯定愿意出钱赎回我的
My husband will see it paid for my return.
我才不要赎金
I seek no ransom.
你要杀了我
You are going to rob me of my life?
不
No.
还轮不到我来杀你
It's not mine to take.
我本来可以一矛戳死它
I could have speared him.
你根本投不了那么远
He was beyond your throw.
难道你比我还了解我能投多远
You know the distance better than my own hand? Do you?
我对神勇的斯巴达克斯可是了如指掌
I know many things regarding the great and powerful Spartacus.
神勇
Great and powerful?
并且正直善良
And kind and just.
我能看穿你的内心
I have peered into your very heart,
知道你是什么样的人
and know what it holds.
如果你在我年轻的时候认识我
You would not have found content so pleasing,
就知道我可不是这么好的人
if you had chanced upon me in my youth.
我那时就是头野兽 没啥人样
I stood more animal than man.
是什么驯服了你这头野兽呢
And what tamed the wild beast?
当然是你的妻子了
Your wife, of course.
对不起
Apologies
杀了葛雷博的老婆
Take the life of Glaber's woman,
就像他杀了你老婆一样
as he took the life of yours.
了结这段恩怨吧
See end to vengeance,
同时了结你为了复仇所造成的一切苦难
and with it the suffering of all caught between you and such desires.
她出事都是我的错
I am to blame for her fate.
如果我没跟甘尼克斯说话
Had I not broken words with Gannicus
他就不会知道伊莉西娅要前往罗马
he never would have known Ilithyia was the road.
你居然说漏了嘴
An unfortunate slip of the tongue.
我以为我能劝甘尼克斯浪子回头
I thought only to convince Gannicus of proper path.
自愿供你差遣 协助捉拿斯巴达克斯
To willingly follow your command and join the hunt for Spartacus.
他可能跟那个该死的色雷斯人勾搭上了
The man is probably in league with the fucking Thracian.
他们俩先前不都是你家的奴隶吗
They were both slaves under your house, were they not?
他们之间隔了好几年
Separated by a distance of years.
从来没有见过面
They never have met one another.
可能只是我们不知道
That we have knowledge of.
不过这都无关紧要了
Not that it is a thing of matter now.
甘尼克斯劫走了我的妻子和未出世的孩子
Gannicus now holds my wife and unborn child.
不知道他们是死是活
If she yet draws breath.
他费这么大力气把她带出城
He would not have risked all to take her from the city
怎么会一刀杀了她
only to have her life.
她还活着
She yet lives.
我心里清楚地感受到她还活着
I feel her heart beating as though it were my own.
你必须派人搜遍城郊的每个角落
Your men must scour the countryside until she is found.
就目前的人手 这要花上好几个月
Such an area takes months to cover with numbers at hand.
那就向罗马求救吧
Then send message to Rome for aid.
这件事绝不能传出去
Word of this shall not spread beyond these walls.
但是伊莉西娅…
But Ilithyia
从罗马民政官的眼皮底下被掳走
Was snatched from grasp of a praetor of Rome.
我可不希望元老院议论
I will not have the Senate whisper
我连自个儿的妻子都保护不了
of how I could not protect my own wife.
明智的决定
A wise choice.
你要着眼于将来
You must look towards your future.
你们居然还谈论政治
You talk of politics?
伊莉西娅是我的朋友 你的妻子
Ilithyia is valued friend and wife.
还怀有你的孩子
She holds the blessing of your child,
这孩子是阿比努斯的遗产继承人
and with him slim tether to Albinius' wealth.
如果找不到她 这些财产就跟你没关系了
One which will be severed if she is not found.
不用你教我事情有多么严重
Do not lecture on what is at fucking risk.
大人
Praetor.
事情办好了吗
You have seen it done?
您妻子出事现场的痕迹都抹干净了
All trace of your wife's misfortune has been erased.
谁也不会知道这件事
No one will know of it.
很好
Good.
叫你的手下集合
Gather your men.
赛皮娅 我有话跟你说
Seppia, I would have a moment.
我要是你 就再也不会这么跟他说话
I would not raise voice in such manner with him again,
如果你希望自个儿还有价值的话
if you wish to keep purchase in this world.
没有了伊莉西娅
Absent Ilithyia's blessings,
这里已经不是我的容身之地了
it is a place that I shall quickly tumble from.
我不会让你落到那般田地的 亲爱的
I would never let you fall so far, my love.
至少目前我还挺喜欢你陪在身边
Not while I yet treasure your company.
很好
Good…
注意观察我肩膀的角度
Now keep eye on angle of my shoulders…
这样你就知道我下一步…
It will give clue to my next
你学得很快
You learn quickly.
我有优势
I have advantage.
有战神亲自教我
Of being taught by a god.
再来
Again.
你他妈打得跟孙子似的
哈鲁德斯 希望你床上功夫比格斗强
哈鲁德斯
Harudes!
你出招时大喊大叫 因此暴露了意图
You betray intent by bellowing like a crazed goat!
他说什么
说你日翻了自个儿的屁眼
纳美特斯人
Nemetes!
萨克莎
Saxa!
就位
Take position.
到时候打仗也用木棍吗
Are we to use wooden stick in battle as well?
闭嘴 听奥诺玛默斯说
Close mouth and heed Oenomaus.
我不需要别人指手画脚
I need no instruction.
我知道怎么打
I fucking know how to fight.
我要教你的不是怎么打 而是怎么赢
I instruct you not how to fight, but how to win.
这样才不会再次被罗马人奴役
So you do not find yourself again enslaved by the Romans.
准备
First position!
开始
Attack!
纳美特斯人说得确实有道理
Nemetes does hold argument.
至少我们武器紧缺是个问题
Towards lack of proper weapons at least.
真见鬼了
Fuck the gods.
你居然把葛雷博的妻子劫来了
You have taken Glaber's wife?
不是
No.
是别人送到我手里的
She has been delivered into my hands.
我要她得到应有的下场
And they will see her to proper end.
婊子
Whore!
快求饶啊
Beg for your life!
我们追求的就是这个吗
Is this our cause now?
欺负一个怀有身孕的弱女子
Falling upon a helpless woman heavy with child?
葛雷博对我妻子何曾有过怜悯
Glaber held no pity towards my wife.
她比你面前这个贱女人更应该活在世上
A woman far more deserving than the thing that stands before you.
混账婊子
Fucking bitch!
你这穷鬼 没钱还敢来花天酒地
Coin before cunt, you worthless shit.
赶紧滚
Now crawl from sight.
给我爬起来
Get up you old cunt!
先别忙走
Linger yet a while,
好兄弟
my good man.
我们非常希望你能在场
We'll have the pleasure of your company.
叙利亚人 你又找我干什么
What do you seek of me now, Syrian?
甘尼克斯
Gannicus.
一个在卡普亚颇有声望的角斗士
A gladiator of some renown in Capua.
有人发现他经常在你的地盘厮混
He has been noted to frequent your establishment,
对不对
has he not?
喝花酒 玩女人
Partaking of wine and whores?
是的 大人
Yes, Praetor.
我有话要跟他说
I would have words with the man.
他不在这里
He is not here.
但诸位中肯定有人
Yet there must be some among you
曾和他一起饮酒
who have that cause to share drink…
或有其他往来
and other distractions with him.
我要知道他说过的话
I would know of what he spoke,
以此找到他的藏身之处
towards revelation of where he secrets himself.
那我想再来一杯酒
And I would hope for another fucking drink
外加一个姑娘
and a whore upon my cock
我再问一遍
Let me ask it of you again.
有没有人和甘尼克斯说过话
Who among you has spoken with Gannicus?
遗憾
Disappointing.
住手
Wait!
我见过甘尼克斯跟人谈话
I did see Gannicus break words!
你说的人是谁
Who was privy to them?
我的奴隶 玛西亚
My slave, Marcia.
她人呢
Where is she?
你手下的叙利亚人把她钉在十字架上
Your fucking Syrian nailed her to a cross.
我还没有拿到应有的赔偿…
And I have yet to receive fair compensation for loss incurred
甘尼克斯夺走了我的东西
Gannicus has taken something from me.
我要找回来
And I will see it returned.
给我严刑逼问
Put all to question.
求你手下留情
Please do not do this…
我妻子在罗马人的屠刀前
Were those same words pleaded by my wife?
是不是也这么乞求过
Before Roman blade ripped her forever from my arms?
我不认识她
I did not know of her.
她的死跟我没有关系
My hands are unstained by the deed.
但你丈夫脱不了干系
Your husband cannot claim such.
是他把我妻子贬为奴隶
He is the one that condemned her to slavery.
她因此离开了人世
She is gone from this world because of it.
我要报仇雪恨
And I will have equal vengeance.
你不能这样
You can not do this!
我的孩子
My child
苏拉和我常说要生儿育女
Sura and I often spoke of children.
说我们要子孙满堂
Of the family we would have,
可现在全都成了泡影
now forever denied me.
我要葛雷博尝尝这样的滋味
As I now deny Glaber of his.
孩子是你的
The child is yours.
你骗人
You lie.
你看我像是在骗你吗
Would that my tongue made false noise.
虽然说起来很讽刺
Yet it sounds bitter truth.
我们在巴蒂塔斯家做过后 我的月事就没了
Monthly blood ceased after you came to me in Batiatus' villa…
露迪雅答应给我克雷斯
Lucretia had promised Crixus.
一个残酷的玩笑
A cruel jest.
你还记得吧 对不对
It is a memory that lingers, is it not?
那晚的事
Of that night.
我们做爱
Of you inside me.
没错
Yes.
尤其是我掐住你喉咙的时候
As does memory of my hands upon your throat.
那就做个了结吧
Then see to completion what they began.
杀了我 还有你的亲骨肉
Take my life, and that of your child.
你的妻子要是知道你做出这等兽行
And may your wife turn from you for what you have done,
日后你们黄泉相见 她不会原谅你
when she greets you in the afterlife.
他以前
真的是竞技场的冠军吗
你不是跟纳美特斯人好上了吗
暂时的乐子嘛
奥诺玛默斯看你回来好像不太高兴
Oenomaus does not seem lifted by your return.
我也没指望你们拿我当兄弟看
I did not think to be embraced as brother.
说实话 我以为再也看不到你了
Nor I or to lay eyes upon you again in this life.
但你还是来了
Yet here you stand.
不是什么事情都这么容易过去的
Would that all things were so easily done.
你们兄弟情深 我是见过的
I have seen the bond between you.
不管有怎样的隔阂
Whatever the cause for disagreement,
总会过去的
it will pass.
为了求他原谅 我什么都愿意做
I would do anything, to rise in his eyes again.
把民政官的婊子捉来 就开了个好头
Capturing the praetor's bitch is a fine start.
这一手太漂亮了
An impressive act,
肯定能为我们的宏图大业助势
sure to further ignite our cause.
我只想结束这一切
I seek only to end it.
解决了吗
It is done, then?
她还活着
She yet lives.
我不惜和罗马决裂
I brand myself fucking enemy of Rome
把她捉来给你处置
to deliver her to your hands.
结果你如此懦弱不堪
Only to find them weak and trembling.
我不是葛雷博
I am not Glaber.
可以毫无怜悯地
Able to strike a woman down
让女人为他的罪孽负责
for his crimes absent misgivings.
那些在卡普亚街头
And what of the women crucified
被钉死的女人怎么办
in the streets of Capua?
她们痛苦地死去 只因为胆敢说出你的名字
Tortured to death because they dare whisper your name,
眼里闪烁过自由和反叛的想法
eyes bright with thoughts of freedom and rebellion?
杀了她 了结这一切
Take the her life and end this now.
否则会有更多人因你而死
Or see countless more fall in the name of your cause.
光是祈祷并不能帮我们走出黑暗
Prayer alone will not provide guidance through these dark times.
我们必须观望自身
We must look inward,
从强大的内心获取力量
and find strength in heart's resolve.
这么说诸神抛弃了你 正如抛弃了伊莉西娅
So the gods turn from you, as they do from Ilithyia?
诸神时刻与我们同在
They are always with us.
诸神的意志存在于每次呼吸
Their will felt in every breath.
每次触摸
In every touch…
他们引导我们的手
They guide our hands,
帮助我们寻找正确的方向
compelling us toward proper course.
盖尤斯听了会很高兴的
Gaius will be pleased to hear of it.
盖尤斯并不是拯救伊莉西娅的关键
It is not Gaius who holds the key to Ilithyia's salvation.
怕是诸神误导了你吧
I fear the gods have led you far astray then.
我既不带兵 也不能召唤出甘尼克斯
I command no army, nor can I conjure Gannicus before us.
但你可以写信让瓦里留斯从罗马过来
Yet message from you would bring Varinius from Rome,
- 他可以… - 盖尤斯说得很明确了
- and with him - Gaius was clear in the matter.
我们不能对任何人说起这件事
We are to tell no one of what has happened.
他这是铤而走险
Words borne of desperation.
他想要保全名声 可现在情况很严重
He talks of shoring name while life's foundation
日子都过不下去了
crumbles beneath his feet.
赛皮娅
Seppia.
你追求过民政官瓦里留斯
You sought Praetor Varinius' affections once.
你的话肯定能够打动他
Send message, and you could yet gain them.
那是小孩子的想法
The whims of a child.
我现在的想法成熟很多 早就没想那些事了
Such thoughts have been set aside in favor of mature pursuits.
忙了一天
The day has been long.
我来伺候你就寝吧
I will see you beneath the covers.
这件事明早再议
We will revisit the subject with the morning sun.
抱歉 我还不想睡
Apologies, I'm not yet for bed.
我去看看盖尤斯
I would check upon Gaius,
说几句安慰的话
and offer words of comfort.
你只是去跟他说话吗
Are words all that you would offer?
我现在是他的客人
I am his guest in this house.
主人这么慷慨 我只想好好谢谢他
And wish only to pay tribute to generous host.
这样不值得 赛皮娅
It's beneath you, Seppia.
诸神肯定有所察觉…
The gods shall take ill notice
不正是诸神之手把哥哥从我身边带走吗
Was it not their hands that saw my brother struck from my side?
是诸神的旨意把我送到这里避难
Their providence that sheltered me beneath this very roof?
你没有看到吗
Do you not see it?
诸神引导我一步步走近盖尤斯
The gods have lead me upon path to Gaius.
正如他们把伊莉西娅带走
As their will has removed Ilithyia from it.
放宽心
Calm yourself.
我不会伤害你
I intend no harm.
那时是你帮了我
You are the one that came to aid.
在我被带进来 那些畜生围着我的时候
When those animals turned upon me when I was brought in.
别对我献殷勤
Do not clutch me to breast.
我和那些畜生一起拉屎放屁
I shit with the rest of those animals.
为了孩子 吃吧
For child.
起码你不会活活饿死
At least you will not die of hunger.
你没有奴隶的烙印
You bear no brand.
你是自由人吗
You are a free man?
我是共和国公民 和你们一样
I am of the Republic, as you and yours.
那你还站在斯巴达克斯一边
Yet you stand with Spartacus against it.
我站在正义的一边
I stand for what is just.
正义
Just?
斯巴达克斯要摧毁我们拥有的一切
Spartacus moves to destroy everything we hold of worth.
我还嫌他的动作太慢了
Then he moves too late in my regard.
苏拉占了我的土地 夺走我的亲人
Sulla seized my lands and those of my kin years ago,
杀死了胆敢抵抗的人
slaughtering any who resisted.
把偷来的东西赏给忠心耿耿的狗腿子
And giving what he stole as gift to his most loyal of men.
他们都是罗马人
All of them fellow Romans.
难以想象你这些年是怎么过来的
Such a loss must weigh heavy in the passing of years.
我可以帮你回到从前
I would see burden lifted.
我以为你自身难保
And I mistake you for helpless,
没想到你还有让太阳西升东落
yet you have power to reverse the sun
改变过去的能力啊
and see past reformed?
我丈夫是罗马的民政官
My husband is a praetor of Rome.
我是他的爱妻
And I of importance to him,
族人眼中的掌上明珠
being prized daughter of my clan,
肚子里的孩子继承贵族血统和万贯家财
my child heir to its lineage and fortune
这种屁话留着跟诸神说吧
Save vaunted words for grander ear.
我不能放了你
I cannot free you.
如果放了你 走不出三步
We would both be absent fucking head
你我都要人头落地
before three steps could be taken.
我不求你放我
I do not ask such a thing.
只要你能替我捎个信
Only that you carry message,
说出斯巴达克斯的藏身之处
imparting where Spartacus holds me.
你不用过这样的生活
You do not have to live this way.
只需我丈夫一声令下
All that was taken from you can yet be restored,
失去的一切都会回到你手里
with but simple command from my husband.
我的损失可不是小数目
The sum of my loss is no small thing.
他肯定能偿还
He can see it paid.
还给你过去的生活
Your life returned to you,
以此交换我
in exchange for mine
以及腹中孩子的性命
and the child I carry.
她说怀着你的种
She claims it yours?
口气十分肯定
With passion of certainty.
真是一条狡猾的毒蛇
She is a deceitful fucking snake,
那张嘴绝对吐不出真话
truth split by forked tongue.
这件事情可能是真的
Her words may hold such in this.
还记得那晚在巴蒂塔斯的宅子里
Do you recall the night in Batiatus' villa,
你帮我扮成金光闪闪的阿波罗吗
when you aided in transforming likeness into golden Apollo?
去伺候罗马女人莱姬尼娅
To lay with the Roman woman Licinia.
她戴着黛安娜女神的面具
She wore the mask of Diana.
结果面具下的却不是莱姬尼娅
Yet beneath it was not Licinia.
是伊莉西娅
Ilithyia.
你为何不告诉我
Why did you not tell me?
告诉你有什么意义
What purpose would it have held?
没有
None.
现在对你同样毫无意义
Nor should it hold any for you now.
即使是真的 她这样说只是为了保命
Even if true, she tells you only to stay your hand.
那她就太蠢了
She's a fool.
让我知道她怀了孩子 而我妻子永远没机会
To know she carries heritage forever denied my own wife…
杀了伊莉西娅
See Ilithyia to her grave.
埋葬那些痛苦的回忆吧
And tortured past buried beside her.
让葛雷博遭受同样的痛苦
To make Glaber suffer as I have
是我日思夜想 求之不得的事情
at his hand is a thing I have craved more than air and breath.
但是做出这样的事情
Yet in inflicting equal wound,
我岂不是变成了跟他一样的人
how do I not become as the man himself?
这是我妻子最厌恶的人啊
A man my wife would turn from.
我先前还不确定你要不要我陪
I was not certain you would desire this.
哪个男人不想要呢
What man could not?
毕竟不是你关心的事情嘛
It is not the offering that gave concern.
尤其是你遇到了这么大的不幸
Rather your preoccupation with unfortunate events.
我不在乎那个孩子的命运如何
The fate of my heir does weigh mind.
那你妻子呢
That of your wife's?
更加不值一提
A thing of lesser notice.
所谓的婚姻就这么不堪一击吗
Is bond of marriage really such a cold affair?
曾几何时
There was a time…
我们也轰轰烈烈地爱过
when the love between us burned hot,
感情炽热如火
bright as noon-day sun.
但是激情最终消退了
But day has turned to night,
那些宝贵的回忆也暗淡无光
casting golden memories to shadow.
我可以让你重新燃起激情
I would have you bask in the light,
像你这样的男人就该如此
as a man of your worth deserves.
阿比努斯可从来没这么看得起我
Albinius did not hold me to such esteem.
元老院的其他人都没有过
Nor the rest of the Senate.
那就拿到斯巴达克斯的人头 给他们瞧瞧
Gaze into their eyes when you present Spartacus' head,
他们肯定对你刮目相看
and see estimation soar.
同时给我哥哥报仇
And my brother avenged.
他的死同样让你很伤心吧
Would that his death did not pain you so.
一天天过去 我也逐渐走出来了
The sting lessens with each passing day.
因为有你
Because of you.
所以我会报答你
And I would return favor,
如果你的妻子跟我哥哥一样
if your wife falls prey to Spartacus,
死在斯巴达克斯手里
as my brother fell…
你的箱子里装满了金钱和鲜血
Your chest overflows with coin and blood.
全是我辛苦赚来的
Both well earned by day's exertion.
伊莉西娅有消息了吗
What news of Ilithyia did labors bring?
你每天就在民政官身边
You have the praetor's ear.
他没有跟你谈起过吗
Did he not already fill yours?
他围着赛皮娅团团转
His attentions toward young Seppia
我连插句话的机会都没有
prevent me from breaking words.
年轻就是资本嘛
Ah, the freshness of youth.
难道他会放着甜美的香唇不吻
Is it a wonder he favors the caress of her tongue
听你唧唧歪歪吗
to the sound of yours?
等伊莉西娅回来 她就失宠了
Her bloom will wither, when Ilithyia returns.
你做这种指望可是相当不靠谱的
You place great stock upon uncertain future.
你没有打听到甘尼克斯的下落吗
You have not found path to Gannicus?
很遗憾没有丝毫进展
Sadly it remains obscured.
不过我真的是尽力了
Though not through lack of noble effort.
我们挨家挨户地打探
From there we moved from place to place,
软硬兼施地逼问
questioning with fist and blade.
可是他们的回答全都一样
The answer always the same.
我要向诸神献祭
I will make sacrifice to the gods.
求他们给出更有价值的回应
And entreat them for more valued response.
我们一起祈祷吧
Let us pray together.
一边爱抚缠绵 一边寻找启示
And seek divinity in warm embrace…
必须尽快找到伊莉西娅和她肚子里的孩子
Ilithyia and the child she carries must be found.
如果找不到…
If they are lost
会怎样
What? Hmmm?
太阳就不会再升起了吗
Will the sun no longer move across the sky?
还是皎月掉进海底不出来了呢
Will ivory moon plummet into frothing sea?
不要再想那个臭婊子了
Strike the bitch from fucking thought,
葛雷博早就不在乎她…
as Glaber has already done
我不是你想打就打的低贱奴隶
I am not your slave to lay fucking hand upon.
我以为你早就想明白了
A lesson I had thought already learned.
抱歉
Apologies.
这话听着不够真诚
I question sincerity of the word.
再说一遍
Speak it again.
抱歉
Apologies.
再说
Again.
抱歉
Apologies
你在这里的地位还说不准呢
Your position in this house continues to spiral.
很快 除了跟着我 你别无选择
Soon I will be all that stands between you and dark abyss.
到了那一天
When the day arrives…
我愿意跟你亲热 那算是诸神的赏赐了
you shall greet my breath upon your neck as precious gift.
你明白吗 亲爱的
Do you understand this, my love?
明白
Yes.
是诸神的赏赐
A gift from the gods…
卢修斯
Lucius.
你要去哪儿
Where do you go?
脑子乱 去醒醒神
To clear troubled mind.
我的脑子也很乱
I would have the same.
我们一起走走吧 边走边聊
Let us walk together for a moment, and break words.
那家伙拿一根木桩出气
The man unleashes wrath upon wooden form.
我为他冒了那么大风险
When I have risked all for him
带来复仇的机会 结果就这样
to seize vengeance and end this.
你只不过是为了减轻良心的不安
You take risk only to lighten weighted conscience.
我不希望更多的人为他送命
I would not see more fall to foolish cause.
更不希望我的兄弟牺牲
And I would not see my brother fall.
我们已经不是兄弟了
We no longer stand as such.
难道我们的关系就没有办法弥补吗
Is there no path towards mended bond?
镜花水月怎么弥补
You cannot mend illusion.
我们的兄弟情
Our brotherhood.
我曾经对你的信任
The trust I placed upon you.
全都是谎言和欺骗
A thing of lies and deceit.
我哪一天不是在煎熬中度过的
Do you not think a day passes that I am not consumed by it?
我愿意拿我的命去换回梅莉塔
I would give my life for Melitta to yet own hers.
这我倒是很乐意
And I would gladly take it.
那怎么不动手呢
Then what stays hand?
你和斯巴达克斯都这么犹豫不决吗
Do you and Spartacus straddle same uncertain ground?
眼前有复仇的机会却不去把握
Unable to take vengeance when it is placed before you?
你的死不能换回她的命
Your death would not see her again to my arms.
杀了你只会让你解脱
It would only serve as mercy,
这种慈悲的事情我不会做
releasing you from what you have done.
看来我只能是罪人
Then I stand condemned,
等到死后才能解脱了
until the afterlife takes me.
你什么都不是
You stand for nothing.
一如既往
As you always have.
我们要等等
We must wait…
等到斯巴达克斯让我们换岗
till Spartacus relieves us of charge.
实在太难熬了
Time passes too slowly…
那我们要速战速决
We must be quick then.
你们就是这么站岗的吗
This is how you stand guard?
抱歉 我们是在…
Apologies, we were…
- 我们在…是在… - 我们…
- Ah, we were we were, we were just - we
上床去吧
Take to your bed.
我来看着伊莉西娅
I will assume watch over Ilithyia.
感激不尽
Gratitude.
求你
Please.
我想再喝点水
I would have more water.
这感觉太可怕了 不是吗
It is a terrible thing, is it not?
活在贫穷与恐惧之中
To live in want and fear.
这就是当奴隶的感觉
That is what it is to be a slave.
求你
Please.
就算是为了我的孩子
For my child.
是真的吗
Is it true?
你跟斯巴达克斯说的那些话
What you told Spartacus?
我向诸神发誓
I swear to the gods.
如果斯巴达克斯杀了我
If Spartacus takes my life,
那他就相当于杀了他亲骨肉
the blood of his child will forever stain his own.
他是个好人
He is a good man.
我不会让他受到这种打击
I will not let him be destroyed by this.
我不会让他杀你的
I will not let him kill you.
你会帮我
You will help me?
对 我会帮你
Yes. I will help you.
帮你离开人世
From this fucking world.
你疯了吗
Have you lost mind?
杀她是迟早的事 我不过代你动手
I move only to spare you from what must be done.
如果你杀了她
If you take her life,
你就永远良心不安
the deed will weigh every breath.
于是你来选择
So you remove choice,
你来接受这样的命运吗
and invite such fate upon yourself?
我可以坦然面对
I would embrace it,
只要你的心不受到折磨
to see your heart spared from the act.
你不懂我的心
You do not know my heart.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus
你走吧
Leave us.
我明确地告诉你
I would have words now.
你在这里的日子结束了
And see your time here at an end.
你有如朝阳般光彩照人
You glow like the morning sun.
想必睡得很香
You must have slept well.
完全没这回事
Hardly at all.
真是太不幸了
It's an unfortunate thing.
我可不这么想
I would not deem it so.
恐怕你应该这么想
I fear you shall.
退下
Out.
我不准你这么威胁我
I will not have you threaten in such a manner.
我这可不算威胁
I do not move to threats.
只是想警告你 那个男人不值得你爱
Only to warning about the man you turn affections towards.
就凭几句话不能让我离开他
Your words will not turn me from him.
我不需要用言语打动你
The time for them has passed.
过来
Come.
我给你看一样实实在在的东西
I have something more tangible to show you
民政官在哪儿
Where is the praetor?
在他房里
In his chamber.
怎么了
What's happened?
有人带来了伊莉西娅的消息
A man comes with news of Ilithyia.
就是你说有我妻子的消息
You claim to have knowledge of my wife?
不只是说说
More than claim.
她在斯巴达克斯的手上
She is being held by Spartacus.
她还活着
She lives?
只是暂时
For the moment.
你怎么知道这些
How do you know this?
我刚从叛军的营地过来
I have just traveled from the rebel's camp.
你也是他的手下吗
You stand as one of his men?
我不是逃犯
I am no fugitivus.
一个疲惫的老头子罢了
Just a tired old man,
希望能在入土之前
seeking what little peace he can
尽可能找到一点点慰藉
before falling to eternal slumber.
只要你告诉我她在哪里
Well, tell me where she's being held
我就重重有赏
and you will be seen to great reward.
你的妻子吹嘘说你很慷慨
Your wife boasted of your generosity
许诺归还我被混蛋苏拉夺去的土地
and promised the return of my lands seized by the bastard Sulla.
这事有可能吗
Is such a thing possible?
这个我能办到
It is within my power.
那我自己的妻子呢
And what of my own wife?
还有我的孩子
My children.
我的兄弟姐妹
My brothers and sisters,
他们全都被罗马人屠杀了
all slaughtered in the name of Rome.
你也能把他们归还给我吗
Is it within your power to return them to too,
婊子养的
you fucking cunt?
动我一根毫毛 你妻子就没命了
Lay a hand on me and your wife dies.
如果我没能按时回去 她也会没命
If I do not return within reasonable hour, she dies.
你要派人跟踪我 她也会没命
Any attempts to follow me, she dies.
斯巴达克斯要我怎么做
What would Spartacus have of me?
盖尤斯
Gaius
说吧
Speak.
你要在太阳初升之前
You are to enter the city of Atella on foot,
徒步走进阿泰拉城
just before rise of morning sun.
你可以带三个人
Three of your men allowed by your side.
斯巴达克斯也是
Spartacus to hold the same.
那伊莉西娅呢
And Ilithyia?
接着她就会回到你身边
She will be returned to you afterwards.
条件是拿一辆马车来换
In exchange for a single wagon,
其中装满盔甲与武器
heavily weighted with armor and weapons.
把军备送给罗马的敌人
Give arms to the enemies of Rome?
这就是他的价码
That is his price.
如果看到你带军队去阿泰拉
If your troops are seen on road to Atella,
斯巴达克斯就不会现身
Spartacus will not appear.
而你的妻子和她肚里的孩子
And your wife and the child she carries,
你就别想再见到了
be lost to you forever.
我有说过动我一根毫毛的后果吧
Did I mention the part about laying hands upon me?
让他走
Let him pass.
我不相信他的话
I do not trust this.
我也不信
Nor I.
但还是要采取行动
Yet action must be taken.
准备一辆马车
Prepare a wagon.
民政官大人 我们给了武器
Praetor, we can not aid them
以后打起仗来就更麻烦了
with means to forge further war upon us.
斯巴达克斯给了我们别的选择吗
What choice has Spartacus left?
不用顺着他的意思
There are always choices.
不
No.
斯巴达克斯只给了一条路
Spartacus leaves but one path.
我只有顺着走过去了
And I must travel upon it.
我老了 但可不傻
I am old, but not a fool.
你这次深入虎穴 我有太多想问你的了
It was much to ask, entering the lair of the beast.
当面羞辱民政官的感觉棒极了
Oh it was great pleasure, to piss in the face of a fucking praetor.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus?
葛雷博答应这些条件了吗
Glaber agrees to the terms?
我要去阿泰拉 完成这笔交易
I am for Atella, to see it done.
我们就拿他的武器
Let us take his weapons!
取了他的狗命
And his fucking life!
不行
No.
如果不信守承诺
If we do not honor word,
那我们就和罗马人没两样
we prove ourselves no better than the Romans.
我们要遵守诺言
We shall hold to it.
如果只能有三个人随你同去
If three are all that can be seen with you,
算我一个吧
I would count myself among them.
我也是 不管与谁同行
As would I, despite the company.
我也要去
I would join as well.
再欢迎不过了
I would welcome no one as warmly.
但你在竞技场受的伤还没有好全
Yet you have not healed from ordeal in the arena.
我来替他
I will stand in his place.
你都不赞同我们所做的事
For a cause you do not believe in?
奥诺玛默斯赞同
Oenomaus believes in it.
也许有一天我也能理解
Perhaps one day I shall too.
记得带趁手的武器回来
Return with proper weapons.
还有你们的小命
And your lives.
只有疯子才会相信葛雷博的话
It is madness to place trust in the words of Glaber.
我不是相信他
I do not place it with him.
而是相信所有跟我同行的人
I place it with all those I take with me.
我们一起完成这笔交易
We will see this done, together.
然后武装起来 让葛雷博及其军队彻底消失
And gain means to strike Glaber and his army from this world.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
那老头说我妻子在你手上
The old man claims you have my wife.
这是从她裙子上割下来的
Cut from her dress.
还有她的气味
Her scent yet upon it.
从她尸体上也能拿到这东西
A thing easily taken from a body robbed of life.
我本来有过这种想法
My thoughts turned toward such a thing.
白刀子进红刀子出
Blade parting flesh.
让她血流满地
Her blood upon the ground,
就像我妻子当时一样
as my wife's blood was spilled.
可你没有杀她
Yet you do not claim her life.
我不像你
I am not you.
我不会让一个女人
I will not strike down a woman
承担她丈夫犯下的罪孽
for the foolish acts of her husband.
你在死人的胸前刻上我的名字
You carved my name into a dead man's chest.
在卡普亚的光天化日之下刺杀我
Make attempt against my life in the streets of Capua.
又在竞技场下手
And then again in the arena.
可你竟然放弃了报仇雪恨的大好良机
Yet you turn from most assured opportunity to balance debt between us.
那不是放弃
I turn from nothing.
不久之后 我定要取你的命
One day soon, I will have your life.
把马车赶到前面来
Bring the wagon forward.
我有很多遗憾
I hold many regrets,
从很久以前我们初次见面开始
since first we laid eyes on each other a lifetime ago.
希望这次不要有什么遗憾
I pray this decision does not stand amongst them.
你的妻子就要重回怀抱了
You will hold your wife again.
她会为你生下子嗣
And she will deliver you an heir.
不过 当你看着孩子的眼睛时
Yet when you gaze into the child's eyes,
总能看到我的影子
I will forever be reflected there…
因为是我饶了你孩子的命
in memory of how I spared them both.
你怕是说对了
I fear you are right.
你跟我不一样
You are not like me.
你妻子是你的心头肉
Your wife was the heart that beats within your breast.
为了保护她 你愿意牺牲一切
You would have given all to see her live.
而我也愿意付出任何代价
While I would do the same…
要你死
to see you dead.
杀掉他们
Kill them!
出手
Now!
找掩护
Take cover!
萨尔维斯
Salvius!
发号
Give call!
撤退
Fall back!
你应该早点叫我们出手
You waited long enough to give signal.
我不能有失荣誉
I cling to honor ignored.
快
Quickly!
别等他们缓过劲来
Before they recover!
快走
Take to foot.
我来断后
I would stay awhile.
卢修斯
Lucius
走
Go.
别等我他妈的恢复理智了
Before I come to fucking sense.
至少不是该死的罗马人杀…
At least it's not a fucking Roman that takes
别让他们进树林
Do not let them breach the woods!
快 快
Go! Go!
你根本没打算做交易
You never intended to make trade?
我打算要斯巴达克斯的命
I intended to send Spartacus to his death.
可这背信弃义的家伙竟然一次次逃脱制裁
Deserved fate he yet evades through treachery and deceit.
你很快就能抓到他了
You will have him soon enough.
牺牲妻子
At price of wife,
还有神赐的孩子吗
and the blessing she carries?
我愿意牺牲整个世界
I would gladly pay the sum of the world
只要我能踩住他的喉咙
to have his throat beneath my heel.
伊莉西娅必须回来
Ilithyia must return to this house.
诸神预见…
The gods have foreseen
如果诸神真想救她的命
The gods can descend from their fucking heavens
那就从天上滚下来啊
if they wish to see her live!
这几天我要哀悼失去的妻子和孩子
In coming days I shall grieve loss of wife and child,
还有她家的那一大笔遗产
and the fortunes carried upon her family name.
我们与你共同哀悼
And we shall grieve with you.
我去洗个澡
I would see myself to bath.
洗掉所有的血迹和烦恼
And blood and troubled thoughts of moment washed away.
去吧
Go.
我去拿酒给你解愁
I will bring more wine to aid endeavor.
你知道他做了什么吗
Do you know what he has done?
必要的事情呗
What he felt he must,
为了干掉斯巴达克斯
to see an end to Spartacus.
他牺牲了整个世界
He has pulled the world to ruin.
逼得所有人活不下去
And with it reason for living.
那是你的担心吧
Your reason perhaps.
我活得好好的
My heart yet beats.
那你哥哥呢
And what of your brother's?
盖尤斯正在替他报仇呢
Gaius moves to avenge his death.
那他应该找自个儿报仇
Then he should turn wrath upon himself,
自行了断
and see it done.
这是你哥哥的 对吧
It's your brother's, is it not?
我以为是奴隶杀了他然后顺手抢走了
I had thought his slaves took it with his life.
其实他们什么都没有干
They stand blemished by neither offense.
你怎么拿到的
How did you come by this?
诸神指引我找到真相
The gods led me to the truth.
藏在阿舒尔的财物当中
Hidden amongst Ashur's treasures.
那些东西都是他杀人后从尸体上取下来的
Stripped from the bodies of those who have died at his hand.
阿舒尔
Ashur?
当时他肯定在场
He must have been there that night,
你哥哥死的那一晚
when your brother fell.
不过这个坏家伙只听命于
Yet the villain moves only upon command
盖尤斯•克罗迪斯•葛雷博
of Gaius Claudius Glaber.
我们失去了太多
Much has been lost.
我们所爱的人
The ones we have loved.
我们以为能永远有他们的陪伴
The ones we thought would forever be at our side.
不过失去了他们
But in their passing,
禁锢我们欲望的锁链也随之打破了
the chains that bound us to desires not our own have been struck.
锁链不打破
And without such a blow,
我们今天也不会在一起
we would not find ourselves in each other's arms.
是啊
No.
确实不会
We would not.
跪下
Kneel.
求你了
Please…
你知道那种感觉吗
Do you know what it is?
爱一个人
To love?
心里充满光明和希望
To be filled with light and hope?
全世界只有那一个人
To see that blessing returned in kind,
最懂你的内心
in the eyes of the only one
你知道这是上天的赐福
that could ever know the true depth of your heart?
而你丈夫夺走了这一切
That is what your husband took from me.
我要让他付出同样的代价
I would take the same from him.
但他选择向我复仇 而不是救你
Yet he chose vengeance against me over your life.
杀了你 报不了我的仇
Taking it would balance nothing.
他不爱你
He does not love you,
而我爱我妻子
as I loved my wife.
你放我走
You let me live?
别以为我是好心
Do not think it a kindness.